Okay, today I want to show you how to
set up a Kubernetes home lab. And we're
going to do this with bare metal on on
an actual machine, a hardware piece of
hardware that we have that we can
install an operating system on and get
Kubernetes up and running. And of
course, we're going to do this with
Talos because it's the easiest way to
get started with Kubernetes on bare
metal. And so behind me on my bench here
is an old Dell desktop. And you can get
old desktops for pretty cheap these
days. I mean, under $100, um, depending
on where you live and depending on what
the specs are. This machine is like an
Optiplex 9990, which came out in 2011.
It'll run Kubernetes great, no problem.
So, let's go ahead and show you how to
get that up and running. So, we're going
to start by heading over to talos.dev to
download the ISO we need. And this ISO
is going to be part of the
documentation. It's actually in GitHub,
but I'm just going to show you where to
find it in the docs. Go to the
documentation and then the Talos Linux
Guides. And this is going to give us an
installation dropdown. And this is a
bare metal platform. This is no
virtualization. We just want to install
the thing. And we have a couple
different ways to install it. And
usually these are like pixie booting
environments or something you have
established. We're just going to go with
the ISO. This is just download an ISO,
put it on a on a USB drive, and then
boot it. And we're going to have two
flavors here. Uh, one is secure boot. If
you're going through the image factory,
which will download and and create the
images for you with different layers,
all this sorts of stuff. We're just
going to get the standard old school
BIOS metal ISO because like I said, this
desktop is 13 years old. It doesn't even
have UEFI on it. It is an old BIOS
machine. There is no I think there might
be some TPM, but no secure boot. So, I
just need the old ISO. And to get that,
we're going to jump over to the Talos
releases page. And this is just a GitHub
release. And in this case, we're going
to have a bunch of different artifacts
that we don't need because again, we're
going to do this on Metal. So, we're
going to search for Metal AMD 64. And
there's our ISO. Let's go ahead and
download that. Now that that's
downloaded, we need to put it on a USB
drive. And there's a bunch of different
flashers you can use to flash an ISO to
a USB drive depending on your operating
system. I like to use Ventoy. If you go
over to ventoy.netss, nets, you can
download this thing that will basically
be like a manager for ISOs on your flash
drive. So, you don't need to extract it
and keep rewriting the flash drive every
time. I have a 64 gig USB drive here.
And as you can see, I just have a bunch
of ISOs on the system. I don't extract
them. I don't rewrite them to the system
or anything. I just download the ISO and
throw it in here. And so, we have our
Talos 167 metal AMD ISO. We just copied
it in. That's all we had to do. And now
we can boot the system from this USB
drive. All right. So I have a tiny Pilot
here that I can connect to the console
and you can see watch it boot. And this
is going to load up and automatically
boot from my USB drive. If you need to
change your settings, you might need to
fiddle with the USB uh boot options. You
can see here I have an F12 to change my
boot options or at least set a temporary
I want to boot from the USB drive. That
completely depends on your hardware.
You'll have to figure that side of it
out. For me, I already set my USB to be
the first boot device because I often
are am booting different things on this
machine. So, once the machine boots from
USB, if you have Ventoy, you'll be
greeted with this uh lovely menu which
has all of the ISOs on your disc. And in
this case, again, I'm using this Talos
167 metal image that we just downloaded.
We can boot that and boot it in normal
mode.
And if all goes well, the system will
start to boot up. You'll see Linux load.
It's going to go to a grub screen real
quick and then give you the initial,
hey, we're actually booting the system.
And again, I'm using this over a Tiny
Pilot, but you can just plug in a
monitor and watch it do its thing. All
right. When things finally boot up,
you'll get to this screen. And this is
the Talos dashboard. This is your local
console, which we have another video of.
You can see a quick tour of it. But the
things we really want to know about in
here is one that we're in this stage
maintenance mode uh up in this top right
corner. Ah, cool. Let me see if I can uh
make this full screen for you. There we
go. That might be a little bit better
with the resolution. I don't know if I
can zoom in anymore, but we'll see uh
stage is in maintenance mode. And we
actually want to see our IP address,
which is over right across from that.
And I get
IP6 192.1686.47.
So, I'm going to need that IP address to
be able to connect to this and configure
it because Talis is all APIdriven.
There's no shell, there's no SSH,
there's no users. Let's generate a
config file and get it
going. I'm going to jump back over to
the docs in the getting started guide,
which is going to show us all the steps
we need to do to turn this into a
Kubernetes cluster and actually install
it. Uh things like downloading Talos
control. Um we can get that as we need
it and basically we need network access.
And so with that, we're going to copy
this command. Taloscont control gen
config. Our cluster name and the cluster
endpoint, which is we only have one
machine, so we have one IP address.
Here's my example command that I'm going
to run. Taloscont control gen config.
I'm going to call this cluster duster
because it's on a Dell. Uh, and then
we're going to have our endpoint, which
is the IP address of the node back
there. And that includes HTTPS because
this is secure with TLS certificates as
well as the default Kubernetes port
6443. This generated our certificates
which is our kind of root of trust and
some tokens as well as a control plane
worker and Talos config. And the Talos
config is for our Talos control command
to be able to talk to the node. And then
the control plane and worker are for the
actual Kubernetes cluster.
So we have that default config, but we
also need a little bit of information
about the box. And with that, we're
going to get the disk information
because we need to know where to install
Talos. So we'll run Talos control
again and run the disk
subcomand discs. And we're going to use
insecure. And insecure is just telling
the API like we're not sending you a
certificate to authenticate. And in
maintenance mode is the only time Talos
is available to make these kind of
queries. So before the machine's set up,
before it's been secured and installed
and locked down, we can query some
information from the machine with an
insecure flag. And this gets a little
garbled with a small screen here. Uh but
you can see here that I have a couple
different uh discs. This is the dev like
/dev path and a model. And that's
usually enough for me to know what I'm
looking at here. And so in this case, I
see a dev on MVMEN1 and a dev of SDA.
And the question is, where do I want to
do this install? And in this case, I can
see that the model of the SDA is a data
traveler. And I know that's the name of
my USB drive. So, I don't actually want
to use that for an installation. I'm
going to want to use this other one,
which has a model number that I don't
recognize, uh, but is definitely an NVME
drive that's internal to the system. So,
we're going to use this NVMe 0N1.
We're going to copy that and we're going
to modify our control plane to specify
that's where we want Telos to do the
install. So I just opened up Vim and
searched for dev slash and I found SDA
is the typical first installation and
again I don't want that because that
would try to overwrite my USB drive.
So,
NVMe 0 and1 and that's the disk we
actually want to
use. Now that we modified the default
templates, we can apply it to the
machine. And we're just going to send
this information to the machine endpoint
API and say, "Hey, I want you to do this
install. Here's your configuration." And
we use the apply config command. Again,
the same nodes is that IP address. We're
still in maintenance mode. So this is an
insecure uh command that we're sending
and then uh the file that we're actually
going to apply. So if I apply this and
I'm going to quickly switch over to my
dashboard here and you're going to see
it's already going to start to do stuff.
Uh here we're going to get this stage is
now installing up here in the top left
as well as the cluster name is already
Deluster. And the the reboot happened
really quickly because it just did the
install. It went through and installed
everything it needed to and it's going
to reboot and reapply those settings. So
the machine just rebooted and now it's
going to go through and do the whole
installation phase. Uh we get a new
stage here of booting because we just
did the install and we get this middle
section here of what version of
Kubernetes we're going to use as well as
things like the cublet the API server
controller manager. All that is going to
be available to me. But we need to do
one more step to kind of get the the
cluster
started. And the thing we need to do to
get the Kubernetes cluster started is we
need to create a database, an SED
database. So here's my bootstrap command
is we're just going to do Talos control
bootstrap. Again, the same node. I only
have one node in the cluster. So it's
also the same endpoint. And then I'm
going to specify my Talos config, which
again is the local file that it
generated for me that gives me the
certificate authentication. So I'm not
doing insecure anymore because Talos has
already done an install and now it's
waiting for authenticated requests. It's
not going to accept any more of that
insecure business. So, we're going to
run that bootstrap command and quickly
switch over to our console here because
again, a lot of this goes pretty quick.
Okay, right when I applied that config,
I hit an error. And this is something
that you should absolutely know about
whenever you're trying to do this. Uh,
you'll see here that I got an UNP RPC
available unavailable error trying to
hit that IP address, my 1
192.1686.47. And that's a little strange
because I just had the machine up and
running. If I switch back to my console,
you'll see here that my IP address
changed up here in the top right corner.
It's now 655. So, if you're doing this
in a home lab cluster, definitely make
sure you set a reserved IP address or a
DHCP reservation on your network for
whatever MAC address you're trying to
get to because these IP addresses can
change even while I'm recording this
video. So, something to make sure you
do. All right, so this is a good lesson
to learn. As I was setting this up, my
IP address changed. And I have two ways
I could fix that. One, I could go
through and set a reservation for the
original IP address that I had and say,
"Hey, I always want to get this same IP
address. I already have certificates
made. I already have configuration
made." That'd be fine. The second thing
I could do is I could set a new IP
reservation of something that I actually
want, maybe not in the DHCP range, and I
can reinstall Talos. And I'm going to go
ahead and reinstall Talos. And to do
that, we're going to go through Ventoy
again, boot off the disc in normal mode,
and when it gets to this grub config
here, I'm going to reset the Talis
installation, and that's the bottom
option here, and it's just going to wipe
the drive for me. It's going to wipe the
disc, reboot again, and I'm going to go
through that same setup. So, when you're
setting this up, make sure you have an
IP address set that's not going to
change because that needs to be uh
consistent in your certificates. Okay,
after a real quick detour there of
setting up a static IP address, we are
back in a booting state. Uh, so we have
the stage of booting and we haven't run
the bootstrap command yet. We have a
stable IP address and and we're
installed. So that's back where we are
and we did apply the control the control
plane config here. The bootstrap command
is an authenticated API call with the
certificates, the client side
certificates that we generated from that
first step of gen config. So now we're
going to apply that bootstrap. We can
see in the log that the started a task
forced for containerd. So we're going to
get ancd cluster up and running. Now we
have a stage of running over here on the
left that went from booting booting to
running. And we have a ready state of
false. So not everything is ready yet.
And we are going to just sit back and
wait because we can see through the uh
logs here this rendered new static pod
API server. Let's actually show you a
cleaner way to get to this as well. You
can do Talos control
dashboard with all the same config. Our
endpoint, our node, all that's the same.
And this gives us that UI. And it's
probably a lot easier to see that uh
here in this stream than what we had
before. And and now this is starting up.
I can zoom out just a little bit there.
Um cublet's healthy, but things are
still going to be running. Another way
to get that information directly to my
terminal without looking at the local
console if it's plugged into something
is Talis control logs. And we're going
to add a follow flag. And again, our
endpoint and node is that same node. Our
Talis config is the one that we just
generated. And we're going to look at
the SCCD service. It's going to stream
the CD logs directly back to us. And so
we can see what's going on with CD.
While the cluster is booting, one other
thing we can also run is something like
the services
subcomand. And if you send it with no
flags, it's just going to give you all
of the services in the cluster. And so
now we can see again the node they're on
our API of Talos itself, containerd, the
CRI dashboard, and then here we have all
the actual Kubernetes, uh, a couple
Kubernetes things, cublets, and CD. And
it looks like all these health checks
are successful. So let's look up the
dashboard one more time and zoom out
just a little bit there. And we can see
that the cublet, the API server,
controller manager, and scheduler all
are healthy. And now we're in a ready
state. So the Kubernetes cluster is
ready to go. Let's go ahead and get a
cube config. We're going to use the cube
config subcomand and the path where we
want the cube config to be written
out. Let's export the cube config so we
can call the Kubernetes
API. K get node. And there we go. We
have one of our nodes in this cluster.
It's a control plane and we have our
version. The last thing I want to do to
this is actually allow me to run
workloads on this because by default I
can't run workloads on a control plane
node. It's a very good idea to keep
those things separated. But with one
machine, I want to be able to run
workloads on it. So let's go ahead and
modify our node config to untaint the
node. So in this case, I'm going to head
back to the docs. And if you search for
how to enable workers on your control
plane node, uh you can see we need to
update our control plane config. So we
have this allow scheduling control
planes true. So let's look at our
control
plane
allow scheduling oops schedule on
control plane true. And in this case
it's the very end of the file. I'm going
to uncomment it. So just like we had it
before, apply config nodes, same IP
address, Talos config and that control
plane YAML which is what we just
modified. I forgot to add my endpoints
because again this is the control plane.
I'm going through that. So now let's
apply it applied configuration without a
reboot. So we could look at all the
pods and we see the typical pods that
would be on a control plane node. Let's
deploy a pod that uh would normally go
on a worker that's not part of cube
system. After applying the config, we
can see that our engine X deployment is
up and running. And if we actually look
at where it's running, um obviously it's
only running on the one machine I have
in the cluster. So this would have
failed before uh but we have to untaint
the node and now we can run workloads.
So even with the detour of not setting a
static IP address, we still went through
and did multiple installs of Talos and
set up our Kubernetes cluster. It's all
ready to go. And now if we want to add
more workers to it, uh we can show you
how to do that in another video. But for
now, you can get started, bootstrap that
old desktop, laptop, whatever, sitting
in a closet and start learning some
Kubernetes.